Washington Housing Association 006
DCPL Special Collections - MLK Library
Washington Housing Association Records
1953-1961
DCPL Special Collections - MLK Library
Washington Housing Association
006
3 Boxes
2 Linear feet
Arrangement
The collection was processed without series.
Biographical / Historical
The Washington Housing Association (WHA) was organized in 1933 as the Washington Committee on Housing to improve housing for low-income residents in the District. WHA sponsored the Alley Dwelling Elimination Act of July 1934. Charlotte Everett Hopkins, a long-time crusader for the passage of the Act, was instrumental in the formation of WHA. Eleanor Roosevelt served as WHA's honorary chairman; Frederic A. Delano was the first chairman; and John Ihlder, a nationally recognized housing activist, was the first secretary. WHA fought for a sound housing code, to insure construction of low-rent housing, and encourage landlord responsibility to tenants. WHA became the Washington Planning and Housing Association in 1962 and later the Metropolitan Washington Planning and Housing Association. In the 1960s the Association assisted residents dislocated by urban renewal, freeway construction, and downtown development find affordable housing.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The records of the Washington Housing Association (WHA) were donated to the D.C. Public Library by Anna S. Miller, a former Executive Director of the WHA.
Scope and Contents
The records primarily contain monthly reports and newsletters of the Washington Housing Association (WHA) from 1953 through 1961. Also included are reports and studies prepared or published by WHA; and testimony and statements submitted to Congress by WHA members on housing issues.
Housing; Associations, institutions, etc; Newsletters; Organizational Records; Low-income housing
- Series 1
  - Interim Report: Landlord-Tenant Court Study, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Southwest relocation data, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Sick Children-WHA publication, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Report on a Study of Condemned Structures, Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Further Views on the Need of a Central Relocation Service, Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Report on Housing Sites, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Report on Urban Renewal in the District (2 copies), 1961 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence to Commissioners from Horsky, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence to Commissioners, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Statements given by staff of WHA, 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Statements given by staff of WHA, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Testimony of staff members of WHA, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Statements made by staff of WHA, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Testimony of staff of WHA, January-June 1959 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Statements and testimony given by the staff of WHA, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Speech of James G. Banks at WHA luncheon meeting, September 30 1959 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Statements and testimony of staff members of WHA, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Statements of WHA staff, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Listing of activities of WHA, 1953-1961 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Monthly reports (includes 1953 quarterly reports), 1954-1961 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Washington Housing Association Newsletters, 1956-1961 (Box 3, Folder 1)